Six Santana stick out of the trunk of this weird car.
Pauly,
42,
is starting his night's work.
It's 11 p.m.
Good night to begin.
Here we go.
He needs a bulletproof vest to go to work.
Welcome to Chicago.
Pauly is a cameraman specializing in crime scenes.
Tonight will be another night of shootings and fires and hopefully not any death,
but typically in this business,
that's what happens.
He hopes there are no deaths.
But he's dialed into the police frequencies and death and injury are his bread and butter.
Chicago has one of the highest murder rates in the U.S.
Another shootout just broke out on the south side.
Pauly has to hurry before the ambulances takes the bodies away.
Hang on one second.
Hang on.
Sure,
sure,
sure.
You're walking into the middle of an investigation.
Just let us figure things out.
Oh,
no,
I'm just trying to stay on your side of the safe here.
Just stay here as always.
There are heavy casualties.
Three wounded.
The shooters were targeting a rival gang.
Two passers-by have been hit.
Typical in terms of the shooting itself.
It's because it's random.
They're going after one targeted person,
but they're hitting everybody in the area with gunfire.
Pauly's been covering Chicago violence for 20 years,
and he's never short of work.
A dozen shootings occur every day.
...devices and things like that.
This is really serious.
This is a war.
There is a war on the streets of Chicago.
...shot at the corner and fires in route 131 East 178th Street.
Barely back in the car,
and there's already a new call on the south side.
The crime played out in front of this house.
The scene is still fresh.
Two new victims of the Chicago streets tonight.
One lightly wounded.
The other hit twice in the chest.
Hey,
Gus This oldie A victim's cousin shows up on the scene.
That's my other cousin.
He's got an handcuff.
He be chillin'.
He just got out of jail,
and he been chillin'
with his newborn baby.
He see something going on now.
The neighbors are all out,
woken up by the shots and screams.
I don't even know why you're outside.
You want to get shot?
Yeah,
in the chest.
Oh,
my God.
I seen,
I'm like,
my son be on this block.
Where my aunt,
my boy,
my nephew at?
I don't know,
I guess the ambulance got him,
mama,
I don't know yet.
They got K-Rock,
they just locked K-Rock up.
My goodness.
I don't know why.
This is not good.
No,
this is not good.
One of the targets was a gang member.
His crew was in the house when the shooting happened.
I gotta call you back,
okay?
Gotta call you back.
This is typically what goes on in this neighborhood every day.
And it don't make no sense.
You can't even enjoy a nice night on your front porch without people getting shot at.
That's what the fuck happened
Called to the scene,
the victim's mother is in shock.
Shattered families,
shootings.
It's daily life in the rough neighborhoods of Chicago.
Gang wars claimed more than 500 lives last year.
Guys,
come on,
come talk to me.
What the fuck?
Somebody tell me something.
I don't have nothing.
7,000 kilometers from Paris,
in the heart of the USA,
lies Chicago.
On the banks of Lake Michigan,
the nation's third largest city is like a beachside resort.
Beaches.
Joggers.
People's minds are far away from the bloody battles just a few blocks away.
With its grand avenues,
its luxury stores,
and its iconic buildings,
Chicago radiates wealth and power.
The city draws over 44 million tourists each year.
They come to see Barack Obama's hometown,
where the president earned his political stripes working as a community organizer on the city's south side.
An area wracked with poverty.
Outside of the rich and touristic downtown lies a violent ring of misery that...
...stretches the entire southwest of the city.
Over 600 gangs are caught up in an endless war.
Of those,
two ultra-violent gangs clash hardest.
The Black Disciples...
...versus JoJo World.
We crying,
we gonna psych them.
Caught up in the tornado of war.
Whoa.
We having a little school.
The gang wars continue behind the bars of one of the country's most crowded prisons.
Half of the convicts here belong to a gang.
Surgeons,
Olivia and Manos are up against 12,000 prisoners.
Their mission,
to end gang reprisals.
The gang issue is on the street,
the gang issue.
is in the jail.
On the streets,
12,000 police officers are deployed against gang violence.
There's a law officer in the area who heard the shots on top of him.
It's a high-risk mission.
He was in the back window.
He started shooting this way.
Hit the bull,
but he never shot him.
War has decimated the gangs,
but more and more now,
it's also creating civilian casualties.
I'm very angry with the people that shoot my children.
On the other end of town,
one community has eradicated violence in their neighborhood.
Do you ever go to the salt side?
With millions of dollars and high-up connections,
the gay community managed to chase out its gangs.
Investigation Chicago,
city of gangs and ghettos.
In the heart of town,
it feels like the 20s.
The old gangster look,
fake bullet holes on the side of the bus,
they call it the Intouchables tour,
after the detectives who chased the world's most famous gangster,
Al Capone,
or Scarface.
As godfather of the Chicago mafia,
he earned the city its reputation as capital of crime.
It's a star attraction.
The tour sells out every day.
Obvious,
natural to have an intentional tour,
a gangster tour in Chicago.
The only place in the world you can have it.
All righty,
shut up.
On the bus,
parents and children get a taste of the local folklore,
firearms.
For two hours,
the guides pull out all the shops.
It's an ambush.
For the finale...
They relive one of Chicago's bloodiest days,
the St.
Valentine's Day Massacre.
After the next 11 seconds,
they would stand there and cut them down.
For tourists,
gang wars are just a game.
Have a nice time while you're here,
honey.
Thank you.
Thank you for coming.
That's what we like to hear now.
Thanks for coming,
buddy.
But on the south side of Chicago,
they are a reality.
As we move away from the downtown,
majestic buildings give way to immense ghettos.
The population is mostly black,
and unemployment is at 50%,
the worst in the country.
Strangers aren't welcome here,
and they don't dare come without protection.
Ex-Marine Ruhi and his colleague Hal
A former policeman are on a mission.
The soldier kept old habits from the war in Kosovo.
His gun always within reach.
Just for last resort,
obviously.
The bodyguard's client is this woman.
She's not a star and not a politician,
just a nurse on her way to work.
In this town,
a suitcase of medicine and a laptop are enough to make her a target.
You need a security there?
Oh yes,
oh yes,
most definitely.
Say anything can happen at any given time.
She could get mugged,
she can get shot,
she can get snatched,
kidnapped.
Shot?
Yes,
shot,
as well as myself.
Why?
I mean,
she's a nurse.
Why?
Because that's where the neighbors,
that's the way some of the neighborhoods are,
and that's the way some people are.
They shot people like that?
Yeah,
straight bullets,
straight bullet does not know anybody.
Yeah,
yeah,
I'll be there.
All right,
bye-bye.
2233.
Their direction,
Roseland,
in the south of Chicago.
One of the city's most dangerous neighborhoods.
In the past seven months,
these streets have seen over 50 people killed and injured by bullets.
We roll down the avenue,
nicknamed the Corridor of Death.
The bodyguards don't try to look tough,
with a plain car and civilian clothes.
Best not to attract attention in this neighborhood.
You done?
No,
no.
You know,
the main focus is not to expose it,
because,
you know,
obviously the main focus is to be discreet.
Still one street to cross to the patient's home.
They're on maximum alert.
A shootout could erupt at any moment.
All right,
so how's he going today?
I'm all right.
All right,
well...
The proof is this young man.
He suffered an accident just a few blocks from here.
He's 33 years old.
He's paralyzed in both legs.
Okay,
all right.
What happened to you?
Yes,
sir.
Where?
There was two right here,
one in my arm,
and two in my back.
Two years and you're back?
Yes,
I'm back.
Five?
Five.
Five shots?
Five shots.
Why?
Argument.
I was arguing.
Arguing with somebody.
We had a conversation.
Just arguing?
About what?
Just arguing.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah.
And the guy blew up to something.
He pulled the gun out.
He wanted to kill you?
Yeah.
They don't look like they want to kill me?
You don't think so?
Yeah?
Five times?
I'd say you shoot somebody once.
The nurse comes every week to check his wounds for signs of infection.
Mike won't say whether or not he belongs to a gang.
More than 600 gangs are concentrated in the west and south of the city.
Layton Kings,
Vice Lords,
Gangster Disciples,
and Black Disciples.
Their territory stretches over half of the town.
The gangs are ultra-violent and caught up in an endless war for territorial control.
They post videos on the internet celebrating victories or declaring war.
The fight goes neighborhood by neighborhood,
street by street.
Injury is inevitable.
The gangs are armed to the teeth and don't hesitate to whip out guns.
These surveillance tapes show an everyday scene in the south side of Chicago.
It's 3 p.m.
The man in blue exits a store into a quickie mart parking lot.
A man in a red shirt walks up with a gun hidden in his vest.
His partner arrives in gray.
Gone out,
they open fire.
The target ducks behind a car and returns fire.
The men trade bullets at close range.
In just a few seconds,
15 shots have been fired.
By miracle,
the man in blue escapes.
He takes off in his car as nothing happened.
Controlling this surge of violence is a serious challenge for the police.
9th District Precinct,
in the heart of the South Side.
6 p.m.
David and Leo go on duty.
They wear bulletproof vests,
machine guns,
and a Smith & Wesson at the hip.
Neighborhood shootouts have been ongoing for the past few nights.
Police patrol the area to try to prevent reprisal attacks.
David and Leo take the call.
Multiple cars converge on the suspect.
Get your fucking hands off me Get your hands off me You got anything on you you shouldn't have?
Where do you live,
young man?
The young man appears harmless.
But Leo and David take no risks.
Their guns drawn.
Okay,
have a good one guys.
We thought it was him.
It's not him.
He didn't have shorts on.
He had jeans,
but he didn't have the jean shorts.
It was the wrong suspect.
But there's still a man walking around with a gun in his belt.
Leo and David have to keep an eye on all the neighborhood gangs if they don't want the situation to escalate.
These guys here,
playing softball in the black.
Most of them are all black and saints.
They're gangbangers?
Yeah,
and they wear the light blue.
You'll see a lot of these guys wearing baby blue.
That's one of their colors that represents their gangs.
For instance,
the guy with the baby.
Yep.
You see the guy with the shirt thrown over his neck and then he's got more baby blue on his jersey.
Colors show gang affiliation,
but members also spray gang tags to mark their turf.
The Razor Sun are the Latin saints.
That doesn't mean another rival gang won't come in and start shooting.
They don't care that there's babies around,
there's young families around.
They'll just start shooting at them.
Their rivals are the 2-6 gang on the next street over.
You see that bunny right there?
That's the 2-6.
Leo and David are on the boundary between two gangs.
Or rather,
their batter line.
On this wall,
the rival 2-6s declared war on the Latin Saints.
When they take their logo or sign or something,
they'll put it down.
We'll show you gang members that have,
like,
halos,
they'll have them upside down.
And it's just basically saying that they're against these guys.
Right.
A little farther,
in the next neighborhood,
is yet another gang's turf.
Two kids caught the police's attention.
The cops know the gang's tags,
their turf,
and also their tattoos.
Yeah.
When was the last time you got locked up?
In November.
For what?
I like you so much.
For shit.
Show me your tattoos.
On his arm,
he has the La Raza Nation sign.
Below it,
there's an upside-down sun,
a permanent mark of their rivalry with the Latin saints.
The tattoo on his face means he's ready to die for this war.
They do this too,
this hairstyle,
the shag,
where they let the back of the hair grow real long.
Some guys will have it down to their butt.
But he's got the same stuff.
The tattoos and haircuts provoke their rivals.
and make them easy targets.
Three bullets in the leg.
But he seems to think it's normal.
Here,
gang members rarely live past the age of
25.
In Chicago,
Those aren't just empty words.
If the gangs are violent,
it's because they're defending their territory,
where they traffic especially in drugs.
Despite police presence,
these neighborhoods are veritable drug supermarkets.
Out here getting this money,
fuck the police.
Over here you're going to see a bunch of boys on a porch.
And all they're doing,
as soon as they hit the street,
all they're doing is selling heroin.
Chicago is one of the most drug-addled cities in the United States.
Heroin and crack ravage the poorest neighborhoods.
In abandoned houses transformed into squats,
drug users come to get a fix,
like this woman in the red t-shirt who's addicted to crack.
Upstairs,
she and her partner get high up to 10 times a day.
On top of smoking.
After just one hit,
the woman cannot even talk.
We're smoking crack cocaine.
At $10 a hit,
she spends $5,000 a month on crack.
To get money,
she's willing to do anything.
I suck dicky,
I sell pussy,
I wash cars,
I sell snow,
I pick up cans,
I do it all.
Sell pussy?
I sell pussy.
Crack is a hell of a drug.
It'll take your body,
your mind,
and your soul.
Your kids,
everything.
Why is crack just a drug of choice?
Because it's my escape from reality.
As she escapes reality...
The gangs stuff their pockets,
and every night,
they kill each other over these millions of dollars in sales.
This evening,
the police scanner announced another reprisal.
It's a shout out between rival Latino gangs.
This way?
Where were they coming?
This way and then hit the alley?
And then they hit the alley right here?
And then they came back around El Rocco.
It's a gold car.
What kind of car?
It's like a...
It's a gold car.
What kind of car is it?
I don't know.
It's like gold.
He was in the back window.
You?
Yes,
I was walking my dogs.
I just took my dogs out.
And next thing you know,
the car came flying right here and stopped right here and started shooting this way.
Where were they?
The back passenger was shooting.
Who were they targeting?
They were targeting me and my guy.
I think they were targeting me.
Most likely,
they were targeting me because they said...
They see my shot.
Because of you?
Because they see my shot.
It's gang affiliated.
So I stop them from going out?
You are gang affiliated?
Yeah.
Which gang?
I keep them as much as possible.
It's a bullet.
When they were shot,
it must have ricocheted and hit the car.
The perpetrators are already long gone.
As with most cases,
Leo and David have no hope of catching them.
One thing is sure,
though.
This attack will be revenged.
Tonight.
Night's till earlier though.
So there might be some.
There might be some.
When?
Either tonight,
tomorrow.
It doesn't,
we just don't know.
Eradicating crime is a difficult task for the police.
They number 12,000 against 100,000 gang members.
And when the authorities arrest them,
the war continues behind bars.
In the life of a Chicago gangster,
Cook County Jail is a rite of passage.
It's the most crowded jail in the United States,
with over 10,000 dead in these awaiting trial.
As an exception,
the jail opened its gates to our cameras.
It is 3 p.m.
Every day,
200 new prisoners arrive.
Jones.
Jones,
you are charged with simple assault.
Your bond is set for $2,000.
You need $200 to walk.
Your court date is the 28th of this month.
I'm going to get your left arm.
Pull that sleeve up.
Turn your arm.
They mark the man on his skin.
What is that?
This number?
This is his inmate
ID number.
These are dangerous prisoners.
Over half of them belong to a gang.
A prison official is in charge of identifying them upon arrival.
Martin,
is that all you have?
You got two dots on you?
Sergeant Olivia is a specialist.
Nothing gets past him.
Come on.
Not your face.
Don't look at me.
Two dots.
Right here?
Right here.
For tutu boy.
He also has...
He's got
31st and where?
That's the block he's from.
No,
not here.
Cameras are rarely allowed in the jail because the situation could ignite at any time.
That's what happened just recently.
Officers rushed to Tier 2B as people and folks gangbanged.
A fight between rival gangs turned into mutiny.
The guards filmed it.
The footage was replayed on American television.
The officers dived in as rivals stabbed each other with deadly shanks.
Inmates refused to submit.
Even as they're overwhelmed by officers.
Stop resisting The toll?
Two prisoners wounded in the shoulder and another in the stomach.
Surgeons Manos and Olivia were hired to prevent this kind of violence.
They've been working here for 20 years.
Prisoners arrive.
We are ordered to step aside.
I don't want you to see something and try to run to catch the action.
I want you to stay close to me.
The jail is divided into blocks of 20 cells.
Inmates live two to a cell of less than eight square meters.
Inmates are not grouped according to gang.
The wardens separate them,
fearing that a group could get out of control.
But even mixed together,
inmates claim allegiance to their gangs.
He's a gangster disciple.
The risk is that rival gangs kill one another.
Each day,
the surgeons make their rounds.
Sometimes the fights will happen right here.
The stairway is blocking the view of the office.
Sometimes the fights will happen in the day room.
Fights might happen in their cell.
But,
you know,
usually they're one-on-one fights,
minor incidents.
Minor incidents.
That's why they have...
me here to go investigate the fights.
I talked to,
what I just did today,
walked around and talked to the deck.
One guy would come out and say,
hey,
the fight happened over
Futsnag. The fight happened over something happened on the street,
you know,
something minus.
Murder
If they seem cautious,
it's because a veritable arsenal is found on the inmates each day.
This is a long threaded bolt that's been sharpened to a point.
And from working at the jail,
I can tell you this is probably a plumbing fixture.
Savage weapons are made from anything the prisoners can get their hands on.
Out of all these weapons,
they appear very dangerous,
but the dangerous ones are the small skinny ones.
These are the days,
because they have the ability to pierce and penetrate.
Makeshift weapons cause about 30 injuries each year,
not to count the reprisals to come.
For Sergeant Manos,
it's a never-ending war.
The gang issue is on the street.
The gang issue is in the jail.
How?
Well,
they don't stop becoming gang members when they come to jail.
They don't stop becoming gang members when they leave the jail.
This is a life choice that they have made.
I'm going to see you,
I'm going to see you.
6 a.m.
the next morning.
Swag,
age 19,
is released after six months for aggravated assault with a deadly weapon.
His friends came to meet him.
My mom ain't coming?
Yeah,
she's down the way.
Yeah.
What up,
what up,
friends?
What's up,
camera,
what's up,
camera?
How was it?
I mean,
you know,
jail is jail.
What happened?
Man,
some violence.
Some violence happened.
I was there.
You know,
they said I was guilty.
Among those waiting is his manager.
Swag is a rapper.
That was good,
right?
Big cars,
green bills.
and pretty girls.
After leaving jail,
the first thing that Swag does is to visit the cemetery.
That's a miracle that gate opened.
This tombstone belongs to his younger brother,
nicknamed Jojo.
He died from gang bullets last year at the age of 18.
I just say every time I come,
it's crazy.
It's crazy to me every time.
Yeah,
it hurt.
It hurt me still,
yeah.
Since his brother's death,
Swag has been in danger.
Yeah,
of course,
because,
you know,
they died too.
It's not just our team who died.
It's people in their team who died too.
So they want revenge,
just like we,
you know what I'm saying?
Want revenge.
Everybody,
it's war.
Are you scared to be shot?
No,
I ain't scared.
When my time come,
my time come.
I ain't scared.
You are 19.
Yeah.
Can you say that?
There's nothing I can do about it,
you know what I'm saying?
So why be scared?
If it happen,
it happen.
This is his younger brother,
Jojo.
They were like two peas in a pod.
Jojo was also a rapper.
This song may have cost him his life.
Gone in hand,
he was taunting a violent gang,
the Black Disciples.
One song was even titled BDK,
Black Disciples Killers.
BDK Swag and JoJo grew up in Englewood,
one of the poorest and most violent areas of Chicago.
Here,
it's a vicious cycle.
Why you put that shit?
What's up?
Swag and JoJo's friends take the same stance toward the black disciples.
You see this mother shit,
but I love drinking.
The only things they do all day are rap,
drink,
and smoke joints.
But now,
they've formed a gang in JoJo's memory.
That's playing the cell phone.
And I'm killing it.
You think that it's your own gang?
It's our own gang.
We crazy
We gon'
cycle We lose it It will almost seem that these boys are joking around,
but they've just shot a music video with a message to their enemies.
The boys declaring war here are the same ones we just saw on the street,
with their fearsome appearance.
They continue the war for their buddy.
Until now,
they hadn't sealed their fates in gang violence.
JoJo became their emblem.
Swag likes to tell about his little brother.
Their house has become a memorial.
This is JoJo's hat,
man.
This is all I got to say.
So this is JoJo's room,
man.
You know what I'm saying?
These are his clothes.
These are his shoes.
These are his fair pair of shoes right here.
You keep everything.
We keep everything just how it was.
Why?
Because we don't want to,
we'd rather not move nothing,
you know what I'm saying?
You miss him?
Of course I miss him.
This is my little only.
This is my son,
and he my daddy too.
I'm his daddy,
he my daddy.
Of course I miss him.
That's all I had in life.
Why do you say he's dead and I dead?
Why do you say that?
We don't have a father.
We never had a father since he was babies.
No daddy,
just mom.
JoJo's is a normal story for a teen adrift in the rough Chicago neighborhoods.
He was a shy child who smiled and behaved.
Angel faced.
A good student.
But his father was absent.
And when JoJo was 12,
everything fell apart.
His father was locked away for drug and arms trafficking.
The two brothers had to fend for themselves.
We don't have nobody to teach us how to be tough in this world,
how to survive.
Besides our mother,
but you know moms want you to do everything good,
positive.
Sometimes these streets not positive.
Sometimes you gotta do bad things in the streets to survive.
Sometimes you gotta be strong in these streets to survive.
Mothers can't really teach you.
Mothers don't want you to fight.
We wanted to meet the Black Disciples,
the gang that JoJo declared war with.
Get my grind up.
To find them,
you have to go deep into Englewood.
Get my grind up.
The gangs come out at night.
It is difficult and dangerous to approach them.
Everybody is an enemy.
It took one month of negotiations before they agreed to talk to us.
The meet-up took place in this project,
at the heart of their territory.
Two men were killed right here.
just a few weeks ago.
In a crowd of children from the project,
we met the gang leader.
Targeted by the police for JoJo's murder,
they all demanded anonymity.
They swagger into the project,
one hand always on the gun.
Man,
this is what it is,
man.
You ain't gotta do it over here like that,
No lackin',
man.
No lackin'.
We ain't doin'
none of it over here,
man.
Take a good look at the motherfuckin'
bad guy.
This your last time seeing a bad guy like me,
you hear me?
Right here.
That damn new generation.
The old block's never died.
Bebe kids.
They never died.
Old block's a little bitch.
At least 15 years in this bitch.
This bitch like a motherfucking war zone to me,
man.
I'm like a fucking Iraqi veteran in this bitch.
Their pockets are stuffed with wads of bills.
They tell us that those thousands of dollars come from selling drugs.
The money?
we'll go to buy guns
Dirty in that thing,
bro.
Everybody got to be out to the ball.
Everybody.
Heavy ammunition.
Heavy artillery.
A lot of guns.
Shout out for everybody.
Hold up.
I'm telling you.
Easy to find.
Real easy to find.
Real easy.
It's raining shells and guns,
man.
It's raining shells and guns.
How you use it?
They call you score.
You kill something,
you score.
And you already use it?
Yeah.
They're going to keep you with something thick.
If you're going to score,
you're going to have something thick on you.
I'm sorry.
tell me.
If you want to live,
yeah.
You want to die,
don't use it.
You'll die.
Tonight,
the black disciples have the party planned.
They let us get in the car with them.
Their hideout is just a few blocks away.
The route is dangerous.
We have to cross JoJo World territory.
Before
getting out of the car with their goods,
one person showed us their carefully packed cargo,
a dozen doses of heroin.
This is for you?
Yeah,
money.
You sell it?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
That's great.
That's what you earn money?
Yeah.
The Black Disciples meet up on the third floor of this building.
The party will reveal information on JoJo's death.
The gang rents this house to throw parties and sell drugs.
Hey,
we could not find no pills.
The police are every block.
We don't sleep here,
we get our money here.
One room serves as a garbage can.
It's a slum.
In a haze of joint smoke and alcohol,
a young boy,
barely 15 years old,
explained why his gang killed Jojo.
What is that?
It's yours?
Which kind of weapon is it?
It's a Glock 40.
How do you carry that with you?
Keep the hops on.
Who eat the hops?
JoJo World.
JoJo World?
JoJo World is the...
They eat some hops.
And what happened to Jojo?
We got his smoke.
People from the BDs?
Why?
To this day,
Jojo's murderer has not been arrested.
But chances are that this death will not be left unpunished.
Yet some neighborhoods have managed to put an end to the circle of violence.
They still live in ghettos,
yet these are white and gay communities.
To the north of town,
on the banks of Lake Michigan,
one area looms large,
Boys Town.
But these bad boys are not gangsters.
Here is Hollywood Beach,
Chicago's gay beach.
An easy breeze and a friendly atmosphere.
Everyone here is smiling and happy.
We are far from the gang wars of the South Side.
I'm trying not to laugh.
Do you ever go to the salt side?
no.
No gangsters or guns here.
Turn around.
That's actually why we come,
like every weekend,
is just to play volleyball.
Every weekend?
Yeah.
All these buff,
bronzed men live just a stone's throw from the beach.
This is their neighborhood,
four blocks and 18,000 residents.
It is an oasis of calm,
populated mostly by men,
often rich and white.
There is no graffiti,
but rainbow flags fly the symbol of the gay community.
Pillars even mark the entrance to the district.
Sean,
29,
lives in a nice apartment.
He's king of the neighborhood.
Do you have a place?
Of course,
yeah.
I have a roommate,
so that's his room.
I apologize,
my boyfriend's sleeping still,
but he knows you're here.
Hey.
Um,
so...
Sean came to try his luck here 10 years ago.
He began as a doorman.
Now he's captain of the Boys Town Nightlife.
You do this every morning?
Every morning.
And if you don't,
what happens?
I don't know.
The minute someone sees you not looking the right way,
they're like,
what's wrong with you?
Are you having a bad day or something?
Sean is meticulous with his appearance.
Feeling beautiful is part of his job.
Okay,
I'll see you later.
Bye,
have fun.
Thanks.
Today is a big day.
Chicago was the nation's first city to have a designated gay district.
Inevitably,
homosexuals reign supreme and they celebrate it.
It is June 30th,
Gay Pride.
850,000 people have come from across the Midwest.
The vibe is sexy and playful.
The only problem?
On one corner,
a handful of anti-gay evangelicals crash the party.
You are not a child of God.
You are a child of the devil.
Shame on you.
That's very clear.
We are warning them that if they don't turn from their sin and turn to Christ,
they will enter the plains of hell.
But the battle was lost before it began.
Fuck you Fuck you Fuck you
And they can do what the fuck they want,
really,
because obviously you see millions of people out here doing what we do every single day.
And how many are they?
There's about fucking 14,
15.
In Boys Town,
nobody can come bully the locals.
Behind them,
they've got serious political support.
For instance,
Pat Quinn is a heterosexual,
married father of two,
and governor of Illinois.
The gay community is a much sought after voting base.
Gay Pride is an essential opportunity to win over votes.
Further on,
there's the county supervisor.
She's also preparing for the next election.
She counts on this rich,
populous,
activist demographic.
But the one getting all the votes leads up the line.
The neighborhood councilmen.
Elected in 2003,
the Gay Council
A man never forgets his neighborhood's influence in the city.
Describable for a city this big to be so supportive of our old city.
If homosexuals receive so much attention,
it is only because they manage a serious feat.
They succeeded where the police failed.
It's hard to imagine that 20 years ago,
this was one of the city's most dangerous neighborhoods.
Look at Roscoe's.
Can you hear me okay or am I talking too loud?
Jim is one of the first homosexuals who settled the neighborhood.
Coming into the patio.
His bar,
Roscoe's,
is an institution.
I've just invited a few of my very closest friends here,
and I'm hoping they're having a good time.
Jim bought this place in the
1980s for next to nothing.
Tucker?
Back in the day,
he was a big fan of the band.
Back then,
it was a Puerto Rican market.
Now,
his bar is worth a fortune.
So telling you a little more about Roscoe's,
this neighborhood was not the great neighborhood it is now.
People were very afraid in this neighborhood because there was gangs in this building,
which became Roscoe's in 1987.
So I came here because I knew it could be better.
I could clean up this part,
and then everything else around it would get better too.
A risky bet.
Given the neighborhood back then,
poverty,
deterioration,
and violence,
upheld by a formidable Puerto Rican gang named the Iron Men.
The mayor at the time,
Richard Daley,
made cleaning up the neighborhood a priority.
In 10 years,
and at the cost of millions of dollars and police reinforcements,
entrepreneurs have managed to make this one of the most linked-in places in American nightlife.
Every weekend in Boys Town,
thousands of homosexuals come and party.
On a single street,
30 exclusive bars and clubs have replaced the city's poorest populations.
No violence,
no guns.
This is how the gay rid themselves of gangs,
with business skills.
Sean arrived here at the right time.
But you have to be creative to last in Boys Town.
He understood.
Ladies.
To pack his nightclub and generate buzz,
twice a week Sean pays $1,500 for these enormous beauties.
I mean we also make it fun,
you know,
we make a variety show.
We do,
you know,
comedy and dance routines.
Come here,
it's backwards.
But the real show is always better backstage,
trust me.
And then you get to learn all of our secrets.
Well,
not all of our secrets.
We can't show that on television.
An hour later,
the drag queens take the stage.
Once again,
Sean has packed the room and the cash register.
While the party winds down in Boys Town,
daily life continues across town.
In the South Side Church,
it's another funeral.
Last week,
another young man was gunned down in the street.
His friends wear shirts with his photo.
As is customary.
He cracked as many jokes as he could.
Family and friends are crushed.
I just have that to look up to.
And I love him so much.
And I'm going to think about him every day.
in eternity praise the lord I am free and no longer bound
He was 26 and the father of a three-year-old.
He belonged to the Gangster Disciples,
a gang with more than 18,000 members.
Many people have come out to pay their respects.
Last year,
gang wars in Chicago killed over 500 people.
And then of course there's the city of Chicago.
More people killed there last year than American troops killed in Afghanistan.
In the south side of Chicago,
there's one neighborhood where mothers have stood up against this violence.
These three women lost their children in a shootout.
Every Friday,
they meet here at a monument to the dead.
My son,
Thomas Lee,
is here.
Marcia lost her son,
Thomas.
He was 20 years old.
My son is Terrell Bosley.
He's the one right in the center.
Pamela's son,
Terrell.
died at the age of 18.
There's Terrell,
there's Dante,
and there's Daria.
Alicia's son wasn't much older.
A hundred photos of children of all ages,
all victims of these gang wars.
The families don't want to stay silent any longer.
They're posting the death stall for all to see.
Teenagers like young Hadia,
aged 15.
Children like Heaven,
and even babies,
like little Jonilla,
who was six months old.
What's supposed to be safe place?
You're supposed to be safe at home,
supposed to be safe in church,
you're supposed to be safe in school.
Where's Terrell?
Terrell Bosley in church,
in church practicing.
Dariel at home,
got shot,
bullet through the door.
I'm very angry with the people that's shooting our children.
I don't even know who shot my son,
but I'm mad at the one that shot my son and the people that drove past and watched my son down the street.
These women haven't finished with their rage.
The slaughter continues as the victims get younger and younger.
It is July 9th.
A young boy is hanging between life and death at the Advocate Christ Hospital here.
His name is Jaden.
The tragedy occurred four days ago.
The parish came together to support the family.
Pastor Wallace organized a vigil to rescue the child.
Anybody out here still believes God is a healer?
Yes Go right outside of this hospital right now.
Jaden is still in intensive care under medical ventilation.
He is five.
The drama took place in this park.
Jaden was playing with his friends.
When two gangsters let out a spray of bullets,
the child was hit twice.
But I came out here to get a prayer through to heaven today,
because that baby needs a miracle.
Jayden's mother is overrun by the media.
The whole of Chicago is in suspense for her child.
He did whatever he had to do.
How is he doing?
Right now,
he's doing good.
I don't think they Wish you didn't hear that he's doing good his vitals are stable
There are so many shootings in Chicago that the press no longer reports them,
but when a child is shot journalists come out
He's a five-year-old kid.
I mean,
he's out there playing with his friends.
I think people are feeling like,
look,
if you can't take your kid to the park and play in the park on a holiday,
then where can you go?
You can't be in your backyard.
You can't walk on the street without worried about being shot.
It's important to let people know that kids,
these innocent victims,
are being shot.
And while people think it doesn't affect them,
I mean,
everybody's affected by a child being shot.
how can you not be?
With the support of her family,
Jasmine spent one month at her child's bedside,
unsure if he would survive.
In the end,
the community's prayers were granted.
It's something of a miracle,
but the little boy finally got to go home.
His family still lives in the same house,
in a seemingly peaceful neighborhood.
Jaden's doing better now.
I already got this kind of spider man,
but I broke the head off.
They did a real good job on him.
Real good job.
No they didn't.
Yes they did.
That was me.
No it wasn't.
Wasn't that the doctor?
It's you?
To save him,
the doctors had to remove his pancreas.
Jaden is going to be diabetic for the rest of his life.
But his mother and stepfather's main concern is the psychological trauma the boy has endured.
Do you remember what happened?
You remember playing in the park with the fireworks,
don't you?
What else do you remember after that,
Jace?
Jasmine would like for her son to be able to talk about the shooting.
What's the last thing you remember playing in the park?
I don't know.
I just think he don't want to talk about it.
But it's okay.
Jasmine hopes to escape this violence.
for the sake of Jayden's future.
I'm getting ready to move.
Yeah?
Where do you want to go?
Out of Chicago.
Yeah?
Far?
Where?
Up.
No one's shooting?
Yeah.
It's a big,
dramatic change.
You okay?
Yeah.
These days,
more and more families fallen victim to gang terror are choosing to flee Chicago,
when they can.